software engineering radio episode 98
rest with Stefan took off
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the
Contras
[Music]
okay welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio we
are here at Opie another conference
where we interview people because during
life interviews with the new gear is
much better than doing the remote stuff
this time we have Stefan took off as a
guest and we're going to talk about rest
and s away and also rest for internet
applications I guess so Stefan welcome
to the show
thanks for having me here so to get us
started why don't you give us a little
bit of an overview what rest is and
where it is used and how it like fits
into the picture of SOA and and all that
stuff everybody talks about ok so to
start very briefly rest first of all as
an acronym it stands for
representational state transfer which is
not the most accessible of terms right
so this is actually mostly due to the
fact that the term has been coined as
part of a dissertation so Roy fielding a
very well-known guy in the web community
actually one of the inventors of many of
the web standards invented the term in
his in his doctoral thesis to describe
one of many architectural styles I don't
think we should dive too too deeply into
all of this because it leads us down you
know a track where many people will
criticize me for using the wrong terms
to express their so um well what what's
what's importantly that rest is a set of
core principles rest as a set of
principles that are independent from any
particular technology so you could you
could apply those principles to any
architecture that you build they can
build something in purely in Java you
could build it in a restful way
recording through to those rest
principles but there is one
instantiation of the rest principles
that is the the best-known which is the
web itself so HTTP and the associated
protocols like a you are eyes are
essentially based on those principles
Roy actually wrote a dissertation after
the fact so some people accuse him of
doing that I've been mending something
yes stealing yeah this is actually
actually he's been involved from the
start in building those and building
those protocols and it's he makes a very
convincing story that actually those
principles have been
have been available without that name as
the core principles underlying the web
okay so I just noticed that I completely
forgot to ask you who you are and I
yourself but I can do this very
elegantly so how is it that you what are
you doing real life what's your job but
you're what do you do so my job and then
and the reason why well I actually deal
with this stuff I'm interested in this
stuff is that I'm I'm actually from
working with a consulting company and we
focus on software architecture and while
in the past we focused mostly on single
systems and trying to find the best way
to to to architect a mission-critical
individual software systems and the
focus has mostly moved now towards
integration so you no longer build a
single stratum you always build a system
of systems and every system has it has
interfaces to others so I'm naturally
interested in in different ways to doing
that I've spent a lot of time using
using carbine and other technologies and
before we found it in OQ which is the
company I work for and when when we
actually found it in a no Q in in 1999
we were doing karma and Java and then we
need to trade to trade to EE and then we
did a lot of web services stuff so for a
long time I used to be a strong believer
in web services and with web services
you mean more or less the XML so
community I wasted mainstream
Ryan streams so our technology so but
more but most people use for building
for building Souls these days yeah and I
was intrigued by this rest thing which I
wish I had heard of and then I I I
started to look into it and there was
some there were very very few people who
actually talked about rest when I when I
when I started to you to get to know it
one of the most vocal ones his mock
Baker when it did it we did a tremendous
service to the industry by very
patiently and and very very I'm
consistently advocating the user rest
wherever possibly trying to educate
people and when he started that
basically everybody thought this guy's
nuts he keeps on ranting about this
stuff that nobody nobody wants to use in
real world and now now we found that
generated so much interest because it
turns out to be a very great thing I
think Mark originally wrote some blog
entry or said something I read this on
Stefano skis blog who recently also
converted to
which is a good sign for us anyway but
he read something that mark has somehow
has gotten demotivated or fed up with
all this war against rest versus
official web service stuff so can you
before we look at rest as as an
architectural style and at its
principles let's briefly visit the war
and what it's all about and then not
mention it anymore just to get this
theological religious discussion out of
the way what is it that that that you
know creates this conflict that there
has been criticism by by the people who
built the web when when web services
were invented so people started
inventing web services as a way to do
distributed computing over Internet
technology so let's use HTTP because
it's deployed everywhere because the
firewalls allow us to put everything
through HTTP let's use that to build the
next generation karma stack so nobody
called it karma for obvious reasons to
come karma was and stuff like that but
people wanted to have the next
distributed objective technology based
on those things and the web folks said
look you you haven't really understood
the principles behind all of this listen
to us for a while and first of all
understand what it is that you are
building upon and build on it in a way
that actually conforms to its to its
architecture and this this was basically
ignored many many people in the web in
the web standards groups and many people
in the in the committee's that actually
use standardized web services did not
have a good understanding of what the
web is about sounds very arrogant for me
to say this but I only admit of fully
admit to having belonged to that
community myself so Napster I was
totally convinced that we need a lot
more beyond basic HTTP to build
distributed systems and how could you
possibly build a distributed system on
just HTTP I mean you need lots of other
stuff on top of that that what was what
I believed so um this this war was
essentially beatbeat between two groups
of people one one of them said look we
know how to build distributed systems
because we've been doing that for years
with Kaba and ratty comm and with other
distributed technologies learn from us
and we'll help you bring the web to its
next to its next face and then we can
use the web for machine-to-machine
integration that was one group
and the other group said look you folks
have failed you failed to build
something like the web on karma all your
all your great theories just don't work
distributed objects are a failure
they're not success when I use something
to when I'm gonna use my web browser to
connect to some web server I'm not using
a ILP I'm using a simple text-based a
simple internet style protocol to do
that so listen to us we know how to
build really scalable internet scale
systems so that was the one that still
is the wallets going on much of it is
based on misunderstandings so many
people see a se advantages and
disadvantages advantages on both sides
simply because they're ignorant of the
other respective features as in any war
as in anyone yes I I fully admit that
I'm on the on the rest side now very
very firmly so I strongly believe that
in most cases rests the best the better
option and F I'm hard-pressed to find
good scenarios for the web services then
that's these days yeah so so then before
we discuss the the rest of in detail
it's important to just say that it is of
course intended for internet style or
business systems I mean if you want to
build I mean just to take the typical
tax mitt example right if you want to
build a network system for a warship or
whatever he's always doing and that's
obviously not something you would do
with rest but probably also not with web
services so it's really not about
building all kinds of distributed
real-time systems it's really about
doing the typical distributed business /
enterprise application or internet
application so I would definitely agree
that it's not intended to be used in
real time scenarios or whatever quality
of service assurances are important and
that stuff where you need those more
maybe sophisticated protocols maybe yes
yes so I would say it's it's applicable
in it would definitely say both are
applicable in scenarios where you have
where one of your goals is loose
coupling right so what you want to have
systems connected but you're not this
term the the world doesn't stop if
forced or no nobody dies if if if the
system doesn't respond in a second or in
a millisecond so obviously that's it's
not real-time capable yeah but it's both
styles I think are applicable in a lot
of scenarios and
I think the the especially the rest
style is mistakenly thought to be only
usable in a very in very few scenarios I
don't think it is okay so let's look at
the details of rest you have this nice
list of five steps or five building
blocks so why don't we step through
those so so the first one is you know
item zero as I says always um I should
actually be careful to not confuse rest
and HTTP because those are two things as
I mentioned before HTTP is just one
example and you could build another
system that is even more restful than
HTTP and and so it's one should not
confuse the two terms those are two
things but for all practical purposes if
we talk about rest and just in common
usage people people are talking about
restful HTTP about using HTTP as
intended and as described in the rest
principle and we can maybe later briefly
revisit the question what other system
could be even more restful or what that
means right right okay so the five the
five things that I think are important
is the first is essentially you you give
everything an ID you you you decide to
to adopt a single consistent naming
convention or identify identify patient
convention for all of your important
things or resources as they're called in
the rest world on the web this this ID
is the URI right so um essentially you
identify things within with a URI and
everything that that merits to be
identifiable gets its own URI and that
is there's a very very key concept that
this doesn't necessarily mean that those
things have to be static or that they
have to be entities in a database on a
persistent sense so you could have a
process step or you could have a salary
increase or you could have you know
whatever a virtual virtual thing it is
that you want to that you want to
identify later on reminds me a little
bit of the early days of object
orientation where people initially
started you know like underline all the
nouns and the requirements and you have
your objects and then over time people
noticed that there is additional class
and objects that you need to make it
system work and you also include those
things as identifiable things exactly
exactly I agree so
you have to you have to think of what
the right resources are and as we will
see Rastus is constrained in in in in
other respects so um you really have to
have more nouns more thing right then
then with other styles the second
principle is that you use those IDs to
link things together there is something
like that that we all know from working
with the web so if I if I put one URI in
in my browser and and and hit enter I
get back some some representation of a
resource that's the terminology right um
so I get a web page for example that
contains links to other web pages to
other resources so a representation of a
resource contains links to others and
linking the other concept of hypermedia
is probably the most important concept
of course it builds on the fact that you
have have IDs so that you can link them
together but this link is a very
important thing and it's not only
important for human consumption
so not only if a user clicks on a link
but you can easily imagine that a
program can also follow a link and you
can connect things together in new and
specifically unforeseen ways so I can I
can aggregate things from a number of
different locations together
and I don't even have to see or I don't
even have to be aware of aware that link
points to right so I can aggregate links
to resources from from different systems
which is only possible because I have
adopted a single consistent
identification strategy otherwise it
wouldn't be purchased to your eye right
and and I guess one of the most let's
say widespread representations is
probably XML and then you can define a
schema where one of the attributes or
one of the elements contains a link to
one of these other things so that's the
way I would create links absolutely I
would I would say that even that the
most widespread representation form one
is actually HTML because that's true I
mean okay well of course for classical
and yeah you know those end-user
applications and those
machine-to-machine things are not as
different as you think they are maybe
that's a funny for us that's one one of
the key takeaways of the whole thing is
that and essentially if you have built a
web UI
according to rest principles then you
are then you are 75 to 85% of the way
you
already mates 85% of the way to working
machine to machine but you still need
the information probably to be a bit
more structured so your program can
reasonably work with it I mean if you
have just crappy HTML that's completely
polluted with layout specific HTML crap
that's not what Union typically XML I
guess if you build it dedicated for a
computer to computer come machine to
machine conversation XML is probably
more suitable I guess yes not to drift
off too far from this particular
principle we're talking about I think
what probably the sweet spot is XHTML we
actually have have a good choice you had
it is XML so yes it's possible by real
XML processor by real XML parser and you
get the benefits of having it both human
readable as well as structure enough to
to put in information and you make sure
that the layout crap is factored out
into CSS all right I completely put it
exactly so which is good style anyway
yes are you okay number three so now you
have those links you have those IDs now
the question is what can you do with an
ID I mentioned one thing in passing
which is that I can put the URI into the
address bar of my browser and hit enter
yeah and this only works because all of
those all of those resources all of
those things objects if you want to all
support a standard set of methods so I
can I can do it get an HTTP GET on any
resource that's identified by a URI and
that's an extremely powerful concept
because this get has this get method
this get verb as he calls it has has a
certain set of semantics defined for it
in the in DHCP specification so I can if
the if the person who implemented this
stuff on the server side has has
followed the specification I can rely on
the get not having any negative effects
for me so an HTTP GET will never
oblige me to anything I will not have to
pay for it I won't have to - I won't get
an invoice two weeks later telling me
that I have to get there should be safe
that had the terminology yeah and there
are other methods namely put post and
delete over the call the four core
methods in HTTP that actually also have
specific semantics assigned to them in
the specification now this is maybe one
case where we can draw the line between
rest and HTTP just to illustrate the
power
rest says you have to have a uniform
interface which is the same set of
methods for all resources and HTTP makes
that specific consists the four methods
they're actually a few more but yeah
core methods have done get put post
delete so this particular instantiation
of rest has these four methods but it
could be totally absolutely possible to
have ten verbs if you want it and and of
course if you think about that your eyes
are more or less now on kind of things
then you probably will need things that
create deletes you know and and gets
those things so it's it's a natural fit
to have those four so every other rest
interface will probably be more or less
probably somewhat similar yes I think
you're right if ever thought about that
as much but you're probably right there
was there were some things like for
example in the in there in an earlier
HTTP draft spec there was a web called
patch which was actually a partial
update right which is a very reasonable
thing to have and actually somewhere
somebody a guy named the guy called
James Snell is actually at the moment
working on reawakening an internet draft
that standardizes patch again so that
could be added the nice thing about
those forward verbs is all about any set
of constraint verbs is that you are able
to build generic tools generic clients
and generic service that can do
something reasonable that or
intermediaries that can do sound
reasonable okay this thing with this
limited set of verbs that is then
generically applied and semantically
reinterpreted right for all those
different things you've underlined
before that's something I was or I still
am a little bit skeptical about that is
the right approach but maybe at the end
of this discussion I'm maybe convinced
see right so we haven't with three of
the five things I think we've mentioned
we have we have the IDS so we have you
you arrive for everything we have links
to link stuff together and have the
standard set of methods to apply to
every to everything to every object next
the next important point is that you
only interact with resources through
their representations yeah so a resource
is a concept that that you never really
see in itself yeah sorry
you know platonic so you you do a get
and you get back one representation of
the result
and in HTTP you have the concept of
content negotiation that enables you to
actually ask for different
representations yeah so for example if I
have a customer that is identified by
some URI yeah I can do a get and say
that I would like to have the the text
slash HTML representation of the custom
and I get back an HTML branch which is
exactly what my browser does when I put
the URI into the address bar or I can
issue a get using a an accept header
that says I had one to have application
slash XML I'll go back get back an XML
representation this concept is very
important because it allows me to
interact with the same resource in
different ways and they're different
with using different representation and
that probably doesn't just extend to
using different to using different let's
say technical data formats you can you
could probably also say I want let's say
that the short summary information about
something as opposed to the more
extensive stuff where is that kind of
going too far I would suggest to use
different resource for that so yeah one
concept I mean it's this is really we
really entering the realm of design
decisions here if you could model stuff
different ways all right practice yeah
that's that's maybe one of the things
that that that is there that are only
just emerging ok I don't think there has
been any agreement on best practices
Heather is a great book by Sam Ruby and
Leonard Richardson called restful Web
Services and it's the one I recommend to
everybody I will put it in the show
notes some guy made it made it made a
nice joke in one of the conference's I
attended lately which was led the Roy
fielding dissertation is the Old
Testament on restful web services the
New Testament yeah I think it was
sanjeev our johanna was one of the the
most entertaining critics okay so
actually the New Testament or the rest
of web service book has a set of well
known well known best practices well
whether they're well known I know but of
best practices I'm not sure what it says
with it with this aspect my personal
recommendation would be to use something
like a SAP resource this is not really a
concept from from I am some rest but you
know URLs can be they don't have to be
but they can be human readable or
hackable as a I'll say yeah so I would
just append an identifier at the end and
to access the services yeah so you would
probably still use this so assuming you
knew you use like in touch
to identify the various whatever
customers then you would use the same ID
for all those variations but you would
you would append something like summary
info basic right okay so that makes it
because I wouldn't like to change the
actual
identity identifier you know the number
that kind of feels wrong to me well you
know you know I'm after you have to get
over you have to get over your technical
knowledge and and forget that the ID is
just the integer I mean the idea now is
the URI yeah and actually if I if I look
at a customer that has an address and a
history of purchases and I don't know
what a region needs assigned to and then
sales representative or um the customer
itself is a reasonable resource so I
have a URI to identify the customer and
I get all of the information but the
customers address is also a meaningful
resource and that has a different at4
right and that ID doesn't necessarily
have to be a hierarchical relationship
the first one it can because it makes it
easier to understand the system yeah you
know but it's not as if it's any and if
it's any part of rest in that respect
sure and there are certainly no
technical requirement right yeah it's
your stomach is probably right okay gut
feeling is also hungry so you know the
last the last thing that's important is
the core as a core principle is that you
that you're supposed to communicate
status lis this this the it's the
restriction on statefulness yep and this
is all this is often misunderstood
because people think well if I can't
have state how can I ever have a
database that this is something
obviously it doesn't mean that you that
you cannot have steady state stored
somewhere there's there's a obviously
resource state it just means that you
shouldn't keep any any client specific
information in a session yeah so
sessions are totally totally opposed to
to rests core beliefs you shouldn't do
sessions well turns session state into
resource state okay but that's isn't
that I mean isn't that in some way a
little bit I mean if you have a highly
scalable web application to certain
state is persisted to database anyway so
what's the difference which is actually
proves my point
I mean the thing is we start that's what
I'm saying there is still every state
that acts as session stage it is meaning
so it doesn't matter how you implement
no there isn't there's there's a huge
difference because if I for example shop
at an at a website and I I have my
shopping cart which I add things to as
in one in one implementation I can send
you a link to that shopping cart right
because it's resource state like say
look Marcus this is identifiable again
yes it's an ADA file I can link to it
okay bookmark it okay and send a link to
somebody else and the other
implementation it's just you know it's
unnamed I find specific state yeah I
think the original motivation for having
a session state was that and database
actions were perceived to be too
expensive yeah so we ended up building
that putting that stuff in memory and
then we noticed well okay now I have it
in memory but now I have lost this
clustered system now but I have to make
sure that if the client hits another
server and it has the state so I
persisted which is absurd it shows that
the the core idea was the right one
that's actually good at good point and I
filled web applications using this
database metaphor myself so yeah so I
think it's it's it's maybe you know you
you may be doing rest or maybe 60 or 80
percent of rest you you may have been
doing rest for a long time just without
being aware of it I was just like you
know if you apply those principles I
think there are just good principles out
of that design you also see many many
web applications even web applications
intended for humans who violate these
constraints one example is the is the
give things an ID constraint so the
identifiable resources constraint
because for example if you look at many
especially in the Java space if you look
at many frameworks they just give you a
single URI and put tunnel everything
through post so you never see a change
in your address bar and if you send a
link to somebody he'll get you'll get
the home page needs to build a session
which is bad depends on what you want to
do you might not as an application
designer you might not want this
temporary data to be available to others
I mean okay if it's if it's not supposed
to be available to others then you have
then you protect it accordingly using
authentication and that's something that
you should do anyway okay so that's a
that's a that's a reason to do for doing
that okay another thing is very
important which is that those principles
are just the the core guidelines and
nobody says you have to
you have to conform to all of them all
of the time so I mean we're all
engineers and if you're building some
makes sense to to relax those
constraints and fancyson yeah so I guess
hmm we successfully stepped through
those five building blocks let's look at
why well of course HTTP in the Internet
is a good basis for doing rest stuff
simply because it has proven that it
works mm-hmm that is there are other
stuff about the HTTP protocol that's
useful in that context so how do you in
other words how do you what are the
features in HTTP that you use to build
scalable high performance applications
yeah so first of all we have to be aware
that HTTP is a very powerful protocol
it's a very it's a very big protocol
it's a complicated one it's one that
that you and I would not design over a
weekend so it took a lot of a lot of
effort of many people to come up with a
thing and it has a lot of features that
many people are only superficially aware
of my favorite feature of HTTP is is
caching so caching is is very
sophisticated in HTTP and it's actually
what makes the web so scalable it
actually enables enables you to to
retrieve a representation of a resource
and in in many different ways and ensure
that you don't retrieve the same
information again unless it's necessary
so for example you can do a conditional
get which means if you do a get on a
representation and then you get on a
resource you get back a representation
which might feature an attack which is a
hash value over some internal resource
state and you send back the next get
with that attack in in a header say ok
sent me the representation if it's
different from this one yeah and the
server will reply with it with a little
appropriate response code that says
notes
it hasn't been modified oddest is relate
to the expires header that's also part
of the caching Crossley do you have
different ways to control you could do
to control caching HTTP you have kind of
time stamps you can have expires headers
that say how long it is ok for a for a
cache to hold yeah the representation
before it needs to ask again that's a
very very sophisticated protocol and on
the web maybe 95 to 98% of all of all
actions are actually read actions are
gets so it makes sense to optimize that
maybe in an eternal
in an internal business applications
that if a number is not 98% sure but
it's still definitely the way over 50s
so it's very important to do that yeah
you also have a very set a very rich set
of of response codes in NHD HTTP status
status codes that actually have sense
from a from an application perspective
because they say for example this
resource has moved it's now so much
somewhere else or this resource is gone
which means it was there before but now
it's no longer or this is temporarily
unavailable this is permanently moved
this is not found this is inferior
vailable but right now I have an
internal server error or this is okay or
I have accepted this request and I can't
answer it right now but I may be able to
do so later so you have a lot of
application level response codes in
there you also have those methods those
application level methods get put post
and delete yeah probably the most
controversial discussion whether those
are really application methods they are
application methods on a certain level
so you could say that the most uniform
interface you know the most generic
interface that you could apply
everywhere would be processed this yeah
though he knows that do it yeah and the
process this has actually been
popularized by by Jim Weber and service
Paris - tedious - very smart guys from
the web services community they said we
have this style called messed it's not
rest its masked it's a message I forgot
the acronym message driven something and
so it's inspired by rest yeah and says I
only have this process this and
everything is in the method a message
basically ever mailbox into which you
drive messages and then the message says
what did you do exactly so that's one
option but the the problem with this
kind of interface is that it's so
generic that it's meaningless I mean it
doesn't say anything just you know you
have you've essentially made it so
generic that all of the meaning is now
in the message yeah rest takes a middle
ground it says I have some level that is
generic across all resources in all
applications which is that there are
certain things that are merely reads
those map to a get there are certain
things that update the resource they
affect there is the resource they are
applied to you map them to put there are
certain things that lead to the resource
being gone and delete there are things
that rely on post which is essentially
on the one side and create a new
resource yeah so it doesn't necessarily
affect the results it's apply to it
might create a new resource and post is
also the generic cop-out methods if you
can't do can't find anything else yeah
and it is a limitation to have only
those four verbs right and that means
that you either have to misinterpret
them in some in some cases or you have
to come up with artificial nouns
artificial things to be able to address
them yes that's the point we had before
right right exactly um yeah I I disagree
with that I would actually try to
convince you that you have to think of
it in terms of object orientation and
inheritance so what you actually do is
you you derive your app your application
specific interface from the rest
application interface which means that
you that you have to take care not to
violate its semantics associated with
those four things it's the Liskov
substitution right you can specialize
right so you specialize yeah and it's
perfectly fine as long as your resource
conforms to the HTTP resource protocol
and it is a valid HTTP resource it may
also be a valid marcos filter resource I
felt a dark specific application
resource so if I'm a client I can
actually be a client on two levels I can
be a generic client and curl or W get or
I am a web browser then I can interact
with your resource based on my knowledge
of the HTTP specification and that's
also true if I'm a cache for example
anima proxy and if I'm the Apache web
server any of the other tons of of
reasonable and very well tested and then
and efficient web software Hans's if I
am a specific client to your application
then I know what I actually do if I do
if I hope one of those methods so I
agree that is a limitation you have to
design differently you end up with more
nouns instead of more verbs yes um but
you gain something which is obviously
you have to yeah you have to you have to
you have to have a good reason to accept
limitations which is that you gain this
widespread
generic applicability you actually
become power of the web instead of
tunneling is that really right and let
me just let me just add to that that's
the one major major point that that the
web folks have criticized
in the web services approach because the
web services approach tunnels everything
through post so let's I mean that's not
true for so one or two in theory
although in practice everybody still
does it and so poner to you can differ
in practice everybody does that
in practice um you also have the concept
of an endpoint yeah which is that you
identify your replication with an ID and
then you have a set of methods in your
service that sits at that particular
endpoint
so essentially you ignore much of the
aspects of HTTP which is which is only I
mean you have to because web services
are supposed to be agnostic Eric also
yes you cannot exploit HTP yeah but
there's simply no way to do that
yesterday and say if they're supposed to
be able to run over TCP or middleware
right you cannot use any of the features
of HTTP to do that so this is simply no
way no way to consolidate those two
worlds so anything else about the HTTP
protocol it's worth mentioning well I
have to say that it's supported
everywhere apparently everywhere in
every client every library and that
programming language has support for
HTTP it's it's extremely well tested
there's some great software for example
I would say that that the that the HTTP
server the Apache HTTP server and that
the squid proxy cache are probably
lightyears ahead in terms of or years
ahead in terms of of quality and
efficiency and and and maturity as
opposed to any ESB you can write to the
software that's that runs half the
Internet have the web runs Apache HTTP D
yeah so there are there are many
probably lots more just to mention some
you could you have built in compression
capability so you the client and the
server can negotiate whether or not to
compress the stuff you can chunk a data
transfer so there's no problem
downloading if you have the bandwidth
there's no problem to download a 1.2
gigabyte or achill installation image
over HTTP you don't do that over web
services and you don't do it over comma
so there's a lot of things that just
work and then have been established over
the course of the time with HTTP so
let's look at the little sample
application or as sample case study and
and contrast the web service approach
with the rest approach just to make
things clear
so I guess the example is usual although
customer stuff so why don't you outline
the solution that you would do with core
ba Web Services WSI whatever let's just
imagine that you want to want to have a
system that handles orders and you
typically have a order management
interface it's the order management
service and if you do a core bar style
interface or if you do the typical web
services mainstream style interface
you'll have multiple operations in this
interface and this operating these these
operations are specific to the task at
hand right you want to build an order
management system so you have one method
that accepts an order let's call it
submit order and it as a parameter it
gets an order object and that gives you
an ID which you go which is of course a
proprietary ID in the scheme of your
order management system right it'll be
47:11 that's the ID you get back you
submit an order and then you have to
pass in that ID if you want to inquire
about an also to have a get order
details and you pass in the ID of the
order and get back an order object or an
order XML
blah blah whatever it doesn't really
matter so you have those operations
let's say submit order and get order
details list all orders delete or cancel
order you probably don't want to delete
you want to enhance markets and still a
market has deleted well so that's a
typical approach well it means is that
you end up with such an interface for
every specific application that you
build which is exactly what it's
designed for
yeah and you also typically have some
sort of description language which may
be code in case of RMA or it may be an
ID l as in case of comma or decock or it
may be a whistle file that says this is
the way I describe it with XML schema
and with it with the stuff that lists
alerts on top now if I map that same
scenario to to a restful HTTP approach I
actually end up with with more nouns
than verbs yeah so um I will have orders
and any every particular order will have
its own ID so the ID concept that is
proprietary and what I just described
will become the mainstream ID concept
which is you arise in the restful HTTP
approach
I will also find nouns for the
collections of
yes that's one of the typical typical
best practices right it's not part of
HTTP or part of rest but it's some of
them has has been established over the
course of time so I'll have a collection
resource that has all my orders and have
another collection resource maybe for my
customers and for Buster it's like Eric
Evans stuff right he has a repository
first stuff this is the main room right
yeah and and you have the things
themselves you have entities and
repositories and both are things objects
and here in this case they're both
resources you can interact with the
collection or with the single thing
right it's a it's a it's a composite
pattern so in this case I think so every
collection resource is also a resource
and contain resources there yeah so but
I don't know that the dddd stuff that
well so I can't really probably yeah so
you have you have more nouns now you
have in the case of the first service
the order management service you would
have a single a single you arrive if you
deployed as a web service in this case
we now have an unlimited number of URLs
because every order and every customer
and every other object your system has
its own ID and now we have the methods
so now we have no we have something like
submit order how do I submit order
submit order if I if I try to find the
matching method in the HTTP application
protocol would be a post because
typically I use a post to create new
resources and the target of that post
that URI that I post to should be the
containing results which in this case is
pretty obviously the orders collection
so I post an order to the orders
collection I came back in a location
either the ID of the newly created order
in the example you have here we are
actually reading this from a bunch of
slides I'm treating here the F also this
hierarchical your eye where you express
that there is a bunch of all those for
given customers so the year I would be /
all of us and then the eye sorry /
customers and then / the customer ID and
then / autos so that's exactly this way
of Hara hierarchically providing more
details about drawings although I have
to warn against I mean one of the things
that many people start when they adopt
rest is they become they become fanatic
about URI design and they spend like you
know ten hour design sessions and coming
up with the right way to structure your
your eyes now I loved readable you are
eyes I think that's a great thing and I
love hackable you are eyes
if I if I look at the um I've been in
the browser it's great if I can just cut
off the last segment and get something
that'll back you know that's that's
there hackable and that's good yeah but
that's oh and it's not in any way as
important as many people think it's good
to have readable your eyes just as it's
good to have readable class names and
readable variable names but you
shouldn't get too too fancy with that
okay so there's a huge difference
between those two things in one scenario
I have I have a service deployed at a
single endpoint and the value that I add
to the web is essentially one URI that I
can post to and I can only post to that
if I know exactly what
application-specific is behind that
there is no way for a generic client to
make any sense
they could build a direct client if you
have the whistle you could generate some
UI that could but you know it's it's
like if it's like I'm try to become part
of this great big web web and I just
hide everything in this great room
behind the door that I could only go to
if I have the key for yeah that's that's
the that's the model yeah if I have the
the rest approach the restful HCP
approach I add a gazillion new resources
to the web that can be linked to for
example I can send you an email and
include a link and an order um I can
build a web page an HTML page that has
that I guess here's my point if you
build a system that is intended to be
used on the internet and integrate with
the internet so you can send links to
resources using email then obviously
using the restful approach is better for
the reasons you outlined I mean there's
no arguing about that however if you
build a district a generic distributed
system that's maybe not on the internet
that's used within an organization maybe
not even this enterprise wide thing
maybe it's just a I don't know a flight
management system which connects info
terminals and and the data back-end or
something why is this an advantage that
you are integrating in some way or shape
or form with the web I don't see an
advantage it's it's a very very good
question I would argue that
organizations internally more and more
resemble the characteristics of the
Internet so they become a combined a new
waste a they they restructure the you
you have a mergers and acquisitions
things change all the time they become
you know the business becomes loosely
coupled because you cannot rely on the
same people being there on the next
floor because they do you know they
might there might be long there
they might work for a different company
or they might or their work might be or
might be offshore to India tomorrow you
have no idea what happens to your
company so it's a good thing to build
for loose coupling as the web as the
internet does the other thing is that
that was a very good point made by Pete
Lacey another another well-known rest
guy and one of the one one presentation
I recently attended I was just that um
people as with the PC revolution people
become used to certain things in private
and externally and they carry that too
right within the enterprise so the fact
that I can do a Google search and find
information on the Internet
might make people think why it's so hard
for them to find information in their
own company so if everything were
exposed as a resource within the company
nevermind the internet just within the
company and you have a single Google
appliance that can work because
everything is exposed as a resource
everything supports a get and everything
returns a readable format then you could
actually do a google search across all
of your companies animations in apps you
could use Microsoft Excel to pull in an
HTML table from from resource and do
calculations on it so there's lots of
benefits that you gain so your point is
basically that there is no point in
distinguishing between an enterprise
system and the internet because both are
actually solving the same problem and
Italy yeah so so it's good to consider
the enterprise a web-like environment
right to a large degree I think that's
true I mean well as security issues I
mean yes some things are even easier if
you're away with it within a company it
might be easier you don't have to defend
yourself against those denial of service
attacks who knows maybe that's that's
going to be a problem within the company
as well yeah you know maybe not as it
not as intentional but you might end up
with the same with the same kinds of the
time yeah so I think we discussed the
the building blocks of rest
let's summarize why people should care
why is it that people should maybe
actively try to learn rest or inform
themselves about the differences between
the two approaches how do you become
informed and why should you so first of
all I think that that the restful
approach has has proven to be very very
scalable very useful very very
successful simply by by because this is
simply shown by the by the web success
yeah look at if you talk to somebody
fifteen years ago about the goals of the
way
everybody would have told you that um
that you would be crazy to expect this
to work and it works very well we were
all relying on it it has really been a
disruptive change within the way we use
we use IT systems so yes that let alone
is a good reason another thing is that
even if you don't even if you end up
building your system to system
communication using web services maybe
for political reasons yes you have no
other option or maybe because the
tooling and the skills of the people you
have is just supportive of this and I'm
as supportive of the rest even if you do
that being aware of the rest principles
will make you build better web
applications for human consumption
because many people just don't know
about these things they they use a get
to to change something as a bad idea if
I link to that to that resource I'm not
really wreaking to resource them if
somebody follows lately I invoke a nice
and I get yeah right that's something is
wrong there people tunnel everything
through post because they're not aware
of any of it yeah so even even if you
only do it for that reason it's it's a
good thing to do that yeah I do believe
that the main argument is that um if you
look at the history of distributed
computing in the last 15 to 20 years you
can see that there's always been this
this goal of this a big it was a system
of this of this set of principles and
technologies that's available everywhere
so that everything can connect to
everything else yeah and I don't know
you you probably remember those of
hollyhock a intergalactic web of
objective that was the first time when I
read them I loved them as it is the
great vision I could have any object on
the planet talked to any other object on
the planet and we all know how that
turned out with Kaba it may be because
of political reasons but still it never
took never worked out the way we please
sure but I mean the day there's two
different problems I mean one problem is
that the fine-grained object kind of
stuff simply doesn't scale so even if
you build a system with Carbaugh people
don't build distributed objects anymore
there build distributed facades or
whatever you want to call this state
typically so that is an architectural
insight that has well that just
everybody knows about so that's not
specific to rest or anything
I agree whatever I wanted to say is
though that um the vision that that
those folks had back when they didn't
total total total fans and I had drunk I
drunk the car
kula that vision actually is much more
realized in in HTTP then in any of
course successes because I really can
now access any resource on the planet I
can call it an object and actually the
actually a European has has as much
similarity to two object orientation and
the nouns the nouns write the notes and
it has the standard set of verbs that's
not common in end in object-oriented
systems but it also relies on the on the
internet style a way of doing protocols
like tech space and very simple very
very easy to understand and I think it's
actually proven that it this is a very
good way to to build those things so I
think it's definitely worth a closer
look and we've seen great success in
building systems so what do you do if
you need transactional at
transactionality security and all that
stuff we're in the website WS star land
you have all these fancy standards how
do you compensate for not having those
things in a rest environment so first of
all let me say that I'm guilty of using
the term WS Death Star which is it has
been invented by David Hyneman handsome
I have to admit though that since I've
used that a while back the the universal
little web services standards has has
become much more reasonable so many
standards are now gone simply and have
been consolidated so much much better
than it was two years ago I'll
definitely concede that but still I
think that many of the many of the
standards although pretty good for
example the ws-security standards are
not bad at all um are simply not used in
practice as much as people like to
believe so for example there's a good
case to be made for message based
security which is supported by WSS but
in practice it's often way too expensive
and not worth the effort so people use
SSL yes people build web services and
use HTTP and SSL and HTTP basic
authentication which is exactly what
you'd use in a rest-based approach - so
there's not really a difference there
yeah um transactions is another good
example I think transactions in a
loosely coupled system are generally a
bad idea I mean especially of course if
you're considering the atomic kind or
2bc kind of transactions yeah there are
other transaction protocols compensating
transactions things like that I have I'm
not a big fan of putting that into
infrastructure I think there's
application logic so I've never run into
that transaction problem as much because
I think you have to
think about if if using a couple
connectors if any loosely coupled
systems there isn't much infrastructure
can do I agree all right so I mean
people some people disagree I'm I'm open
to to debate here yep everything there
and if you have if you have for example
a case where you need to integrate
existing systems that support to precede
transactions using open XA you may be
better off using using something else
yeah then rest them it's also a very
important point there's lots of cases
where restful a chip is not the best
option but I doubtful whether the
alternative should then be web service
right sometimes Kaba might be a better
series you have an existing course is
sometimes a JMS on-message yes that's
what I meant I think there is no point
in trying to play rest against I had the
extreme example with real-time quality
of services or if you go back to let's
say messaging backbone application
infrastructures in a big enterprise rest
is really an alternative for cases where
you would use WS star stuff yeah that's
what yes - I don't understand you that's
that's perfectly perfectly reasonable
okay so before we wrap up this thing I
would like to ask one thing about
tooling you mentioned it before in
passing there is all those Web Services
tools where you pass in an Vistal file
and it generates all those you know
stops and stuff so what kind of tool
support is available for rest and maybe
the question should ask before how much
tools appall is actually necessary
considering that it's Internet Protocol
taste one of the nice things that has
happened in the last review the web
services space is that that two concerns
with regards to lean have become
separated that that were merged together
before which is the separation between
the actual and invocation and the data
binding so earlier versions in
especially in the javelin had had a
single approach for that now you have
with with jax-ws successor to Jack's RPC
you have the choice of using your data
binding basically any java web service
to cloud to do the same thing you can
have any data binding and of course you
can use exactly the same data binding
tools with rest yeah assuming you do XML
because most of this data bennington
yeah our XML yes but you also have data
binding tools that allow you to to do
Jason - alright excellent it's really
yeah if if you're a fan of data binding
and I'm not if you are a fan of data
you can use the same tools in both
worlds okay the same same thing so the
question is do you need something that
generates a a stop for you that has has
submit method I mean you know the
difference it's not that big a
difference they don't have that anymore
than right on the end post yes in the
rest way too beautiful you you use the
same methods all the time again I'm a
generic submission right interaction
thing that's said I'm actually probably
I'm actually actually a member of the
expert group on jsr 311 in the Java
space which is the Java API for restful
web services and that's an API that is
in typical typical current Java fashion
annotation Trivium and gives you a very
easy way to expose java objects as
restful resources and in contrast to
many other standards in this space it's
it's been done by people who really
really understand a rest net we're
talking about myself talking other guys
there yeah really understand it and
we're trying to avoid all the typical
mistakes and even even refueling is
involved with this not actively but he's
viewing all of that and making sure
we're not doing anything dumb there yeah
so um I'm not that big a fan of of
annotations of annotations in Java so I
have my problems with that as well but
still I think it's a good way to to
enable mainstream mainstream programmers
using the mainstream programming
language now easily build systems have
conformed to those constraints so I
think the tooling is getting better and
even within the web services space where
you have that much tooling you often end
up building worse systems because of it
so I'm skeptical of any sort of tooling
anywhere
okay so let's this let's rev up this
episode maybe with summarizing a couple
of important takeaway points why don't
you just do this I guess you know what
they are so one of the things is that
many of the promises that the web
services on WS star space I think are
questionable and you should really you
should really ask yourself whether these
are really things that you need and
things that are really that you really
gain some benefit from so my favorite
example will be protocol independence
yeah which is something that is so leaky
you know it's not you're not you're not
abstracting all your protocol at all if
you've ever tried to build something
that works equally well over JMS and
HTTP you'll find out that this protocol
independence is
is not really that true yeah I think
that you need to distinguish between
abstracting away the protocol as an
implementation of an interaction
paradigm and trying to abstract away the
interaction paradigm you can't do that
you can't appoint executive points right
so the absolute IMS is so totally
different than HTTP me right but you can
abstract away messaging infrastructure
the one you choose and say you have you
just know it's messaging yeah I know but
if I just know it's messaging I can use
JMS I mean that's a that's an API I
could use yeah and I have customers
where they have different languages and
they can't use chairman salt and just
don't I don't want to spoil your the
first thing is there is a there is a
there's a promise associated with web
service exactly that I think is
questionable because you can either use
this stuff that web servers are supposed
to encapsulate or you can use or you can
go down the full restful HD premium I
mean after all Web Services are supposed
to create a single widely deployed a set
of protocols and everybody can use
personally I would rather use a set of
YTD protocols that's already there then
waiting for another one to become
available that adds no value for me it's
like I I think protocol I think there's
also Mike Baker quotation I think
protocol independence is embarking on a
feature yeah I saw that before the next
one would be I think it's perfectly fine
to standardize on standards so many
people are afraid to standardize on HTTP
which I don't get I mean you don't
become dependent on any single vendor
and you pick a standard and stick with
it it's like wanting to abstract away
whether you store your data in XML
database or in a relational data
database or in flat files I mean
sometimes you have to make decisions and
you shouldn't be afraid to make
decisions and you just pick one of them
yeah it's perfectly fine to do xml over
your messaging system of choice if you
have decided to use a websphere mq
anywhere everywhere which is something
that many companies do why would you
want to abstract that away - no - no
benefit doesn't really give you much
yeah and maybe the last thing is I think
you should really understand the
WebSocket extra even if you later decide
not to use it you should understand it
um and my obvious recommendation would
be you should understand it as well well
enough so that you can exploit its
benefits for example all the scalability
things the interoperability
caching chunking compression all that
stuff that really leads to your to you
being able to build better systems okay
Birgit searched anything else you want
to say prose of wisdom you want to leave
with our listeners as the gamma space
show always says pose of wisdom I don't
know but maybe one of the things that
I'm really happy that I think it's now
starting that we're moving beyond this
this this versus that my you know it's
like this has not been very very
productive I think it was necessary for
some time to to make to make people
aware of rest if now they are and now
I'm really happy that we can move on and
they actually try to come up with those
back prep best practices that you
mentioned with typical solutions to
difficult problems and I'm really
looking forward to the next few years
and everyone very good then I thank you
very much for being on the show thanks
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SD - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the dick reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team place an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle